So I'll be taking off for the next three papers.
그래서 나는 다음 세 편의 논문을 위해 출발할 것입니다.
So essentially what we're discussing today has been,
그래서 오늘 우리가 논의하고 있는 내용은 본질적으로 다음과 같습니다.
how do we speed up inference and techniques surrounding it?
이를 둘러싼 추론과 기술의 속도를 어떻게 높일 수 있습니까?
Nothing really locked to the particular model and
특정 모델에 실제로 고정된 것은 없으며
that would be a common trend even for
그것은 심지어 일반적인 경향이 될 것입니다
the papers which I'll be going through.
내가 검토할 서류.
So as a starter,
그래서 스타터로서,
at least for the three papers which I'm covering,
적어도 제가 다루고 있는 세 편의 논문에 대해서는
and in the past weeks at least what we have looked at
그리고 적어도 지난 몇 주 동안 우리가 살펴본 내용은
in improving the LLM efficiency.
LLM 효율성을 향상시킵니다.
We have been mostly looking at how do we speed up the training aspects,
우리는 주로 훈련 측면의 속도를 높이는 방법을 살펴보았습니다.
and not really how do we deploy these models in scale.
실제로 이러한 모델을 어떻게 규모에 맞게 배포할 것인지도 아닙니다.
In the last lecture, we had some aspect of what is
지난 강의에서 우리는 무엇인가에 대한 몇 가지 측면을 다루었습니다.
a good architecture to be able to deploy these models on scale.
이러한 모델을 대규모로 배포할 수 있는 좋은 아키텍처입니다.
But that would come under most of the first three categories,
하지만 이는 처음 세 가지 범주의 대부분에 속합니다.
for example, and what we'll be looking at today is the last four.
예를 들어, 오늘 우리가 살펴볼 것은 마지막 4개입니다.
So we'll be covering speculative,
그래서 우리는 추측을 다룰 것입니다.
so we are primarily looking at reducing latency and improving throughput,
따라서 우리는 주로 대기 시간을 줄이고 처리량을 향상시키는 데 중점을 두고 있습니다.
and that's the common theme across all the papers.
그리고 그것은 모든 논문의 공통 주제입니다.
Some of them target one of those,
그들 중 일부는 그 중 하나를 목표로 삼고 있습니다.
some of them try to improve both of them,
그들 중 일부는 두 가지 모두를 개선하려고 노력하고,
and we'll be covering speculative decoding,
우리는 추측적 디코딩에 대해 다룰 것입니다.
BLLMs as the solution for doing this.
이를 위한 솔루션으로 BLLM이 있습니다.
So yeah, for the first paper,
네, 첫 번째 논문에서는
we want to efficiently handle LLM requests that are coming in.
우리는 들어오는 LLM 요청을 효율적으로 처리하고 싶습니다.
So LLM applications have been something which are on the rise in the recent days,
그래서 최근에는 LLM 지원이 늘어나고 있습니다.
and let's say you have a co-pilot at Cilsrani,
Cilsrani에 부조종사가 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
and every single time you make an iteration on the code,
코드를 반복할 때마다
there's an API column going to the co-pilot server and it's responding to you.
부조종사 서버로 가는 API 열이 있고 여러분에게 응답합니다.
So when there are millions of requests coming in,
따라서 수백만 건의 요청이 들어오면
how do we efficiently handle them and make use of
어떻게 효율적으로 처리하고 활용합니까?
the infrastructure which we have at hand?
우리가 가지고 있는 인프라는 무엇입니까?
So yeah, so let's look at regular inference procedures.
네, 그럼 일반적인 추론 절차를 살펴보겠습니다.
We already had a look at KQB at attention,
우리는 이미 KQB에 대해 관심을 갖고 살펴보았는데,
but let's just look at what actually happens during the inference stage.
하지만 추론 단계에서 실제로 무슨 일이 일어나는지 살펴보겠습니다.
So let's say we have an input token coming in,
입력 토큰이 들어오고 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
we convert it into an embedding,
이를 임베딩으로 변환하고,
let's say x, and then we multiply it with weight matrices which we have learned.
x라고 가정하고 여기에 우리가 배운 가중치 행렬을 곱합니다.
So we have Wk, we have Wq, we have Wv,
Wk, Wq, Wv가 있습니다.
so the key query and value weights,
핵심 쿼리와 값 가중치,
and then we compute K for Kv,
그런 다음 Kv에 대해 K를 계산합니다.
and then let that just be small q,
그리고 그것을 작은 q라고 합시다.
and then we have K and then V being computed based on these weights.
그런 다음 K와 V가 이 가중치를 기반으로 계산됩니다.
So that's a matrix and let's say this is a vector,
이것이 행렬이고 이것이 벡터라고 합시다.
and this is the embedding of the input token coming in.
이것은 들어오는 입력 토큰을 삽입하는 것입니다.
So what we are primarily interested is in K and V,
그래서 우리가 주로 관심을 갖는 것은 K와 V입니다.
at least for the first paper.
적어도 첫 번째 논문에서는요.
When they're computing attention through the dot product of,
그들이 내적을 통해 주의를 계산할 때,
let's say qA transpose divided by root dimension of this,
qA 전치를 이것의 루트 차원으로 나눈다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
and then we take the softmax and then we multiply with the value matrix.
그런 다음 소프트맥스를 취하고 값 행렬을 곱합니다.
So if we are doing this computation,
따라서 이 계산을 수행하면
the naive way to do it,
순진한 방법으로,
we would end up recomputing each of the elements in the QK transpose matrix.
결국 QK 전치 행렬의 각 요소를 다시 계산하게 됩니다.
So to avoid having to recompute every element,
따라서 모든 요소를 ​​다시 계산할 필요가 없도록 하려면
we have new query tokens coming in for a sequence.
시퀀스에 대한 새로운 쿼리 토큰이 들어옵니다.
We implement something called the KvCache.
우리는 KvCache라는 것을 구현합니다.
How does the KvCache work?
KvCache는 어떻게 작동하나요?
So let's say I have a sentence saying I am no good,
그럼 내가 좋지 않다는 문장이 있다고 가정해 봅시다.
and we need to do this for each of the input tokens coming in,
들어오는 각 입력 토큰에 대해 이 작업을 수행해야 합니다.
and as we do that,
그렇게 하면서
we keep building a KvCache for each token.
우리는 각 토큰에 대해 KvCache를 계속 구축하고 있습니다.
So let's say each of these is a token which is coming in.
그럼 이들 각각이 들어오는 토큰이라고 가정해 보겠습니다.
We create the K matrix and the V matrix,
K 행렬과 V 행렬을 생성합니다.
we store this in memory,
우리는 이것을 메모리에 저장합니다.
and each of these tokens,
그리고 이 각 토큰은
so here it will correspond to a particular column in the K matrix,
따라서 여기서는 K 행렬의 특정 열에 해당합니다.
and here it will be a particular row in the V matrix.
여기서는 V 행렬의 특정 행이 됩니다.
As we do this over time,
시간이 지나면서 이렇게 되면서
these matrices are growing in size.
이 행렬의 크기는 점점 커지고 있습니다.
So we can say that instead of
그래서 우리는 대신에 이렇게 말할 수 있습니다
recomputing this entire matrix or redoing that computation,
이 전체 행렬을 다시 계산하거나 해당 계산을 다시 실행하고,
what we can do is that for all the previous tokens,
우리가 할 수 있는 일은 이전의 모든 토큰에 대해
we can have Kcache,
Kcache를 가질 수 있고,
which is all the columns which have computed so far.
지금까지 계산한 모든 열입니다.
I just save it into my cache.
저는 그냥 캐시에 저장합니다.
Then when new tokens come in,
그런 다음 새로운 토큰이 들어오면
I just add it to my cache,
그냥 캐시에 추가하고
and this is the only new computation which I do,
이것이 제가 하는 유일한 새로운 계산입니다.
and the same thing for the value matrix,
값 행렬에 대해서도 마찬가지입니다.
everything which has come so far,
지금까지 온 모든 것,
I save it into my Vcache,
Vcache에 저장하고,
and then the new computations go into a new row in the Vcache.
그런 다음 새로운 계산이 Vcache의 새로운 행으로 이동됩니다.
So as you can see,
보시다시피,
as we have a large sequence length,
시퀀스 길이가 크기 때문에
our K and V matrices will keep growing in size.
K 및 V 행렬의 크기는 계속 커질 것입니다.
Now, in the nine implementation,
이제 9개 구현에서는
we need contiguous chunks of memory for this
이를 위해서는 연속된 메모리 덩어리가 필요합니다.
because of the attention operations which will be happening.
앞으로 일어날 주의 작업 때문입니다.
So the first paper looks at how we can break this down
첫 번째 논문에서는 이를 어떻게 분해할 수 있는지 살펴보겠습니다.
and manage memory better.
메모리를 더 잘 관리할 수 있습니다.
So what exactly does the KvCache contain?
그렇다면 KvCache에는 정확히 무엇이 포함되어 있습니까?
As a high-level overview.
높은 수준의 개요입니다.
So let's say this is my prompt.
이것이 나의 프롬프트라고 가정해 봅시다.
So we have that,
그래서 우리는 그것을 가지고 있습니다.
and then this is the current snippet,
이것이 현재 스니펫입니다.
and the model is generating the response,
모델이 응답을 생성하고 있습니다.
and we are currently stopped at IAM.
현재 IAM에서 중지되었습니다.
So at this particular snapshot,
그래서 이 특별한 스냅샷에서
we have four tokens,
4개의 토큰이 있습니다.
but let's say this is a model with a 2048 context length.
하지만 이것이 2048 컨텍스트 길이의 모델이라고 가정해 보겠습니다.
You can also, if you have worked with the OpenAI API
OpenAI API로 작업한 경우에도 가능합니다.
or any inference calling,
또는 추론 호출,
you can specify a max tokens for how much you want to generate.
생성하려는 양에 대한 최대 토큰을 지정할 수 있습니다.
So there is an issue of variable sequence lengths,
따라서 가변 시퀀스 길이 문제가 있습니다.
which we should keep in our minds,
우리가 마음속에 간직해야 할 것,
but let's assume that we have a 2048 sequence length.
하지만 시퀀스 길이가 2048이라고 가정해 보겠습니다.
So essentially, I'll be reserving memory for those 2048 tokens,
따라서 본질적으로 저는 2048개 토큰을 위한 메모리를 예약할 것입니다.
and that's shown by the reserve token.
이는 예비 토큰으로 표시됩니다.
And the model can also choose to terminate early.
그리고 모델은 조기 종료를 선택할 수도 있습니다.
So if you gave me a request,
그러니까 나한테 부탁을 했다면,
and I'm done with my response,
답변을 마쳤습니다.
I can pass the US token,
미국 토큰을 전달할 수 있고,
and then I'm done with what I needed to do.
그러면 내가 해야 할 일은 끝났습니다.
So this is just a snippet of what is happening into the future,
따라서 이것은 미래에 일어날 일의 일부일 뿐입니다.
and this particular response ends at that US token.
이 특정 응답은 해당 미국 토큰에서 끝납니다.
And then towards the end,
그러다가 마지막으로 갈수록,
that green is another prompt which has come in,
그 녹색은 들어온 또 다른 프롬프트입니다.
and the model is serving back.
모델이 다시 서비스를 제공하고 있습니다.
So this is just a snippet of memory,
그러니까 이것은 단지 기억의 한 조각일 뿐입니다.
and what the authors are like,
그리고 작가들은 어떤 사람들인지,
the problem which the authors are trying to solve.
저자가 해결하려고 하는 문제.
So as we can see,
보시다시피,
we have two issues,
두 가지 문제가 있습니다.
which the authors call internet fragmentation
저자는 이를 인터넷 단편화라고 부릅니다.
and external fragmentation.
그리고 외부 단편화.
So because of the reserve tokens,
따라서 예비 토큰으로 인해
we have a big chunk of memory being allocated
우리는 할당된 메모리의 큰 덩어리를 가지고 있습니다
as the request came in.
요청이 들어왔으니까요.
And because we do not know the output lengths
그리고 우리는 출력 길이를 모르기 때문에
of to what extent this model is going to consume memory,
이 모델이 메모리를 어느 정도 소비할 것인지,
we also have some padding between the next token
다음 토큰 사이에도 약간의 패딩이 있습니다.
being saved into memory.
메모리에 저장되는 중입니다.
So we have external fragmentation happening as well,
따라서 외부 단편화도 발생합니다.
because of the different sequence lengths,
시퀀스 길이가 다르기 때문에
and internal fragmentation is because you don't know
내부 단편화는 당신이 모르기 때문에 발생합니다
the output length of where this will terminate.
이것이 종료되는 출력 길이.
So what the authors find is that
그래서 저자가 발견한 것은
based on this naive allocation of memory,
이러한 순진한 메모리 할당을 기반으로
about 60% remains unused.
약 60%는 사용되지 않은 상태로 남아 있습니다.
So that's the problem which they are trying to solve.
이것이 바로 그들이 해결하려고 하는 문제입니다.
And code wise, if you want to turn off cache
캐시를 끄고 싶다면 코드를 현명하게 사용하세요
and turn on cache,
캐시를 켜고,
we can just use the use cache in TensorFlow.
TensorFlow에서 사용 캐시를 사용할 수 있습니다.
And if you try to do that on Colab with like a T4,
Colab에서 T4와 같은 장치를 사용하여 해당 작업을 수행하려고 하면
it will have a performance difference of like five X.
5X 정도의 성능 차이가 있을 것입니다.
So we do need KV cache,
따라서 KV 캐시가 필요합니다.
but we need to do it efficiently,
하지만 효율적으로 수행해야 합니다.
and this nine way doesn't work.
그리고 이 9가지 방법은 작동하지 않습니다.
Just the serving the entire memory block
전체 메모리 블록을 제공하는 것뿐입니다.
for the entire sequence length.
전체 시퀀스 길이에 대해.
So you can free our cache.
따라서 캐시를 비울 수 있습니다.
Yeah, we cannot be pre-allocating this memory.
예, 이 메모리를 사전 할당할 수는 없습니다.
To do it efficiently,
효율적으로 하기 위해서는,
there should be some better way to handle this.
이 문제를 처리하는 더 좋은 방법이 있어야 합니다.
And that's what the authors propose in this paper.
그리고 이것이 저자가 이 논문에서 제안한 것입니다.
Again, just to look at the scale of things.
다시 말하지만, 사물의 규모를 살펴보십시오.
Before the presentation,
발표에 앞서,
I just had a look at how much code Lama consumes.
방금 Lama가 얼마나 많은 코드를 소비하는지 살펴보았습니다.
So essentially we have,
본질적으로 우리는
let's say,
의 말을하자,
so we have two matrices.
그래서 우리는 두 개의 행렬을 가지고 있습니다.
So K and V.
그래서 K와 V.
And then we have,
그리고 우리는
since for inference, we usually do FT16.
추론을 위해 우리는 보통 FT16을 사용합니다.
So we can say that's two bytes.
그래서 우리는 그것이 2바이트라고 말할 수 있습니다.
And then we need a number of layers.
그런 다음 여러 레이어가 필요합니다.
So code Lama, if you look at the biggest 60 billion
그러니 코드 라마, 가장 큰 600억을 본다면
parameter model,
매개변수 모델,
if you look at the 60 billion parameter model
600억 개의 매개변수 모델을 보면
for code Lama.
코드 라마를 위해.
So that would be approximately 120 GB,
그러면 약 120GB가 됩니다.
just for the model rates.
단지 모델 요금 때문입니다.
But what I'm trying to look at is how much
하지만 내가 보려고 하는 것은 얼마나 많은가이다.
the KV cache would be.
KV 캐시가 될 것입니다.
So the number of layers for the 60 billion parameter model
따라서 600억 개의 매개변수 모델에 대한 레이어 수는
is 80.
80입니다.
And the embedding dimension of the 60 billion parameter model
그리고 600억 개의 매개변수 모델의 임베딩 차원
is 8192.
8192입니다.
Unlike some of the smaller models,
일부 소형 모델과 달리,
which have 510 and so forth.
510 등이 있습니다.
And yeah, so essentially we have multi-client on this.
그리고 네, 본질적으로 우리는 이것에 대한 다중 클라이언트를 가지고 있습니다.
So we have two into two bytes into 80 layers
따라서 우리는 80개의 레이어에 2바이트를 2바이트로 구성했습니다.
into 8192.
8192로.
And again, we have batch size coming into the equation.
그리고 다시 한 번 방정식에 배치 크기가 포함됩니다.
But for inference, batch size essentially deals with
그러나 추론을 위해 배치 크기는 본질적으로 다음을 다룹니다.
how many requests are we processing
우리가 처리 중인 요청 수
rather than the training batch size.
훈련 배치 크기보다는
So even if we keep this as one,
그래서 이것을 하나로 유지하더라도
we are only serving one at a time.
우리는 한 번에 하나씩만 서비스하고 있습니다.
If you complete this, it comes out to 10 GB.
여기까지 완료하면 10GB가 나옵니다.
So just, so the KV cache,
KV 캐시는
assuming full utilization of the context length
컨텍스트 길이를 완전히 활용한다고 가정
would be around 10 GB.
10GB 정도 될 겁니다.
So yeah, so this is like a parent model
그렇군요. 이건 부모 모델 같군요.
which we have deployed, right?
우리가 배포한 것 맞죠?
So code Lama 2 is one of the best,
그래서 코드 라마 2는 최고 중 하나입니다.
I wouldn't say best, but for some tasks,
최선이라고는 말할 수 없지만 일부 작업의 경우
a good open source model.
좋은 오픈 소스 모델.
Is that 10 GB per batch or 10 GB?
배치당 10GB인가요, 아니면 10GB인가요?
Yeah, so it is per request, in a sense.
네, 어떤 의미에서는 요청에 따른 것입니다.
Is that reused or does he pilot it?
재사용한 건가요, 아니면 조종하는 건가요?
So once you're done, you can obviously free it.
따라서 작업이 끝나면 분명히 해제할 수 있습니다.
But let's say like...
하지만 말하자면...
Yeah, that is the maximum you can consume
응, 그게 네가 소비할 수 있는 최대치야
for a request.
요청을 위해.
How much is the cost of 8,192?
8,192의 비용은 얼마입니까?
Yeah, and this becomes even bigger of an issue
응, 이게 더 큰 문제가 되네
if you consider the new Gemini models which came out
새롭게 출시된 Gemini 모델을 고려한다면
because they boast like 10 million context length.
왜냐하면 그들은 천만 개의 컨텍스트 길이를 자랑하기 때문입니다.
So yeah, you can see like,
예, 다음과 같이 볼 수 있습니다.
we cannot allocate that much memory contiguously
그렇게 많은 메모리를 연속적으로 할당할 수는 없습니다.
and we should only be allocating what is required
필요한 만큼만 할당해야 합니다.
at this point of time
이 시점에서
so that we can process multiple requests as they're happening.
여러 요청이 발생하는 대로 처리할 수 있도록 말이죠.
If you exceed this memory, obviously it will crash
이 메모리를 초과하면 분명히 충돌이 발생합니다.
and you cannot do anything about it.
그리고 당신은 그것에 대해 아무것도 할 수 없습니다.
So as far as what the authors concern,
그래서 저자가 우려하는 바에 따르면,
they look at 13 billion parameter model
그들은 130억 개의 매개변수 모델을 봅니다.
and it consumes around 30% of the available memory
사용 가능한 메모리의 약 30%를 소비합니다.
for the KV cache.
KV 캐시의 경우.
I was just trying to make the point
난 단지 요점을 말하려고 했을 뿐이야
that it's much bigger of an issue right now
지금은 그게 훨씬 더 큰 문제라는 걸
if you do it naively.
순진하게 하면.
Yeah, so we cannot have contiguous spaces of memory
그래, 그러니까 우리는 연속적인 기억 공간을 가질 수 없어
being allocated for such huge sizes
그렇게 큰 규모로 할당되고
and memory sharing is something which cannot be done
그리고 메모리 공유는 할 수 없는 일이에요
in the naive implementation.
순진한 구현에서.
Why do we need to do that?
왜 그렇게 해야 합니까?
We'll come to in a later slide.
이에 대해서는 이후 슬라이드에서 다루겠습니다.
Yeah, so this sounds like something we study in OS
네, 이게 우리가 OS에서 공부하는 것 같군요.
about memory fragmentation and sharing.
메모리 조각화 및 공유에 대해
Like that's essentially what the authors do as well.
그것은 본질적으로 저자도 하는 일과 같습니다.
So you can make a logical simile.
그러면 논리적인 비유를 할 수 있습니다.
So you're considering incoming requests as processes.
따라서 들어오는 요청을 프로세스로 간주하고 있습니다.
You're considering that we define something
우리가 뭔가를 정의한다고 생각하고 계시나요?
as logical KV blocks
논리적 KV 블록으로
which is essentially same as virtual memory
이는 본질적으로 가상 메모리와 동일합니다.
and you also define physical KV blocks
물리적 KV 블록도 정의합니다.
which is the representation in actual physical memory
이는 실제 물리적 메모리의 표현입니다.
and that physical memory.
그리고 그 물리적 메모리.
And similar to a page table, you also define a block table.
페이지 테이블과 유사하게 블록 테이블도 정의합니다.
So what do the authors propose?
그렇다면 저자는 무엇을 제안하는가?
Instead of allocating the entire contiguous block
전체 연속 블록을 할당하는 대신
which we just computed the size of,
방금 크기를 계산했는데,
we instead break it down into smaller blocks
대신에 더 작은 블록으로 나눕니다.
of let's say size four in this particular example
이 특정 예에서는 크기가 4라고 가정하겠습니다.
but it's better to use 16 or 32 based on experiments
하지만 실험에 따르면 16이나 32를 사용하는 것이 더 좋습니다.
which we'll look at later.
나중에 살펴보겠습니다.
And if you have blocks of size four
그리고 크기가 4인 블록이 있다면
and we're kind of abstracting out
그리고 우리는 일종의 추상화를 하고 있어요
some implementation level details of like
다음과 같은 일부 구현 수준 세부 정보
we are storing K and V for each of these KV blocks.
우리는 이러한 KV 블록 각각에 대해 K와 V를 저장하고 있습니다.
But so essentially you have in the logical table,
하지만 본질적으로 논리적 테이블에는
everything's contiguous but in the physical table,
모든 것이 연속되어 있지만 물리적 테이블에서는
you're essentially mapping it using the block table
본질적으로 블록 테이블을 사용하여 매핑하고 있습니다.
to non-contiguous chunks within the physical table.
물리적 테이블 내의 연속되지 않은 청크로.
And yeah, so as the model is generating a new token,
그리고 예, 모델이 새 토큰을 생성하는 동안
it has this block reserved for it.
이 블록이 예약되어 있습니다.
So it will add it to the block
그러면 블록에 추가됩니다.
because it has available memory.
사용 가능한 메모리가 있기 때문입니다.
But now I want to add a new token.
하지만 이제 새 토큰을 추가하고 싶습니다.
I do not have space anymore in the two blocks
두 블록에 더 이상 공간이 없어요
which I have reserved.
내가 예약한 것.
So now I need to request for another block
이제 다른 블록을 요청해야 합니다
and that block is allocated to it.
해당 블록이 여기에 할당됩니다.
And to complete this particular request,
이 특정 요청을 완료하려면
I use two more blocks in that four block group.
저는 그 4개의 블록 그룹에 2개의 블록을 더 사용합니다.
So the block table is just enabling you to make that mapping
따라서 블록 테이블을 사용하면 해당 매핑을 만들 수 있습니다.
and keep track of as you need to expand.
확장이 필요한지 계속 추적하세요.
So obviously if you scale this to multiple requests,
따라서 이를 여러 요청으로 확장하면
you can do the same thing.
당신도 같은 일을 할 수 있습니다.
You will have individual block tables
개별 블록 테이블이 있습니다.
for each of the requests,
각 요청에 대해
but it can essentially do the same thing.
하지만 본질적으로 같은 일을 할 수 있습니다.
But something to note here is this is a particular
하지만 여기서 주목해야 할 점은 이것이 특별하다는 것입니다.
kind of example which I picked.
제가 선택한 예입니다.
You have the same prompt,
동일한 메시지가 표시됩니다.
but there are two different responses happening.
하지만 두 가지 다른 반응이 일어나고 있습니다.
So which is a kind of decoding which you can do
그래서 당신이 할 수 있는 일종의 디코딩은 무엇입니까?
of parallel decoding or and if you want to do,
병렬 디코딩을 수행하거나 원하는 경우
for example, if you want open AI
예를 들어 개방형 AI를 원하는 경우
to give you two choices of responses,
두 가지 응답 선택권을 제공하기 위해
like if you have just interface with the chat GPT API
예를 들어 채팅 GPT API와의 인터페이스만 있는 경우
using GPT-4 or even GPT-3.5,
GPT-4 또는 GPT-3.5를 사용하여
it will sometimes show you like,
때로는 다음과 같은 내용이 표시됩니다.
hey, these are two responses which I have.
안녕하세요, 제가 받은 응답은 두 가지입니다.
Which one do you think is better
어느 것이 더 좋다고 생각하시나요?
and then they use it to improve their model.
그런 다음 이를 사용하여 모델을 개선합니다.
But it is something which is actively used.
그러나 그것은 적극적으로 사용되는 것입니다.
And if you want to do that,
그리고 그렇게 하고 싶다면,
this doesn't seem like a good way to go about it
이건 좋은 방법은 아닌 것 같아
because you are again wasting memory
왜냐면 넌 또 메모리를 낭비하고 있으니까
for the common bits of these requests.
이러한 요청의 공통 비트에 대해.
So, and yeah, before I jump into that,
네, 그 문제에 뛰어들기 전에
we do have internal fragmentation,
내부 단편화가 있습니다.
but it is limited because it is limited by the block size
하지만 블록 크기에 의해 제한되기 때문에 제한됩니다.
because you only reserve that much.
왜냐하면 당신은 그만큼만 예약하기 때문입니다.
And then if any internal fragmentation does happen,
그리고 내부 조각화가 발생하면
it's because you're not consuming
그건 네가 소비하지 않기 때문이야
that much of the block size.
그 정도의 블록 크기.
And there is no external fragmentation by this logic
그리고 이 논리에 의한 외부 단편화는 없습니다.
because you're requesting more memory assignment required.
더 많은 메모리 할당이 필요하기 때문입니다.
So, there is no concept of external fragmentation.
따라서 외부 단편화라는 개념이 없습니다.
Now, how do we share KB blocks?
이제 KB 블록을 어떻게 공유합니까?
So, let's say we are doing parallel recording
그럼, 병렬 녹음을 한다고 가정해 봅시다.
and we want two responses for this particular problem.
우리는 이 특정 문제에 대해 두 가지 응답을 원합니다.
What the authors propose is we have something
저자가 제안하는 것은 우리에게 뭔가가 있다는 것입니다.
like reference counts.
참조 횟수와 같습니다.
So, for both of these sequences,
따라서 이 두 시퀀스 모두에 대해
we have blocks with a reference count of two.
참조 횟수가 2인 블록이 있습니다.
I said two requests are depending on this right now.
지금은 이에 따라 두 가지 요청이 있다고 말씀드렸습니다.
And let's say at this point, I choose to diverge.
그리고 이 시점에서 나는 분기를 선택한다고 가정해 봅시다.
I choose to have two different tracks of responses.
나는 두 가지 다른 응답 트랙을 선택했습니다.
What I'd do is reduce my reference count to one.
내가 할 일은 참조 횟수를 하나로 줄이는 것입니다.
And then there is an operation
그리고 수술이 있어요
which is allowed called copy on write,
쓰기시 복사라고 불리는 것이 허용됩니다.
which essentially copies the block
본질적으로 블록을 복사합니다.
which you're working with.
당신이 함께 일하고있는 것입니다.
And then only that is repeated.
그러다가 그것만 반복됩니다.
And then today we are learning
그리고 오늘 우리는 배우고 있습니다
what still has a reference count of two.
여전히 참조 횟수가 2인 것.
And then you can continue on this in the normal flow.
그런 다음 일반적인 흐름으로 계속 진행할 수 있습니다.
Another case which the authors try to demonstrate
저자가 보여주려고 하는 또 다른 사례
of like they can support is beam searching.
그들이 지원할 수 있는 것은 빔 검색입니다.
So, it is supported through fork append and free operations
따라서 포크 추가 및 무료 작업을 통해 지원됩니다.
which is again part of their implementation.
이는 다시 구현의 일부입니다.
And what exactly is beam searching?
그리고 빔 검색이란 정확히 무엇입니까?
So, if you're doing something like machine translation,
따라서 기계 번역과 같은 작업을 수행하는 경우
there are often like as you progress through the sequence
시퀀스를 진행하면서 종종 다음과 같은 현상이 발생합니다.
and you are creating the,
그리고 당신은
like let's say I'm computing English to German.
내가 영어를 독일어로 계산한다고 가정해 봅시다.
And as you proceed through the sequence,
그리고 순서대로 진행하다 보면,
the model may decide that,
모델은 다음과 같이 결정할 수 있습니다.
oh, this particular interpretation
아 이 특별한 해석은
which I thought of it is not really the best way.
내가 생각한 것은 실제로 최선의 방법은 아닙니다.
I should probably have thought of it in a different manner.
아마 다른 방식으로 생각했어야 했을 것 같아요.
So, beam search allows you to maintain
따라서 빔 검색을 사용하면 다음을 유지할 수 있습니다.
particular beams of thought.
특별한 생각의 광선.
And the issue with this as compared to parallel
그리고 병렬과 비교했을 때 이것의 문제는
is that beams can be deleted
빔을 삭제할 수 있다는 것입니다
and you can have new beams just up here.
여기 바로 위에 새로운 광선이 있을 수 있습니다.
So, like beam one got deleted
그래서 빔 1이 삭제된 것처럼
and now the new beam one is the earlier beam zero
이제 새 빔 1은 이전 빔 0이 됩니다.
and a branch of it.
그리고 그것의 가지.
So, this is again supported by this model of memory sharing.
따라서 이는 이 메모리 공유 모델에서 다시 지원됩니다.
And yeah, another thing which is required for one,
그리고 네, 또 하나 필요한 것은,
the reason that there was a reason
이유는 이유가 있었어
why we had contiguous memory.
왜 우리는 연속적인 기억을 가지고 있었는가?
And that was to like efficiently support
그리고 그것은 효율적인 지원을 좋아하는 것이었습니다.
these attention computations, right?
이런 주의 계산이죠, 그렇죠?
So, the authors also introduce page detention
그래서 저자는 페이지 디텐션도 도입했습니다.
which is, they just implement the kernels
즉, 그들은 단지 커널을 구현합니다.
to handle the different blocks in this case.
이 경우에는 다른 블록을 처리해야 합니다.
So, essentially it's just a rewrite
따라서 본질적으로 다시 작성하는 것입니다.
of the original equation.
원래 방정식의
You compute it per block
블록별로 계산합니다.
and even the values are for that particular block
값도 해당 특정 블록에 대한 것입니다.
and then you assimilate it back into the attention score.
그런 다음 그것을 주의 점수에 다시 동화시킵니다.
So, you can see the attention computations happening
따라서 주의 계산이 일어나는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
for each block, so I move through it.
각 블록마다 이동합니다.
And yeah, then you can just iterate over all the blocks
네, 그러면 모든 블록을 반복하면 됩니다.
and compute the attention score for it.
그리고 그것에 대한 관심 점수를 계산합니다.
So, what was the results of the authors, fine?
그럼, 저자들의 결과는 어땠나요?
The authors re-implement ORCA.
저자는 ORCA를 다시 구현합니다.
So, ORCA is not completely available.
따라서 ORCA를 완전히 사용할 수는 없습니다.
So, they re-implement ORCA and then compare
그래서 그들은 ORCA를 다시 구현한 다음 비교합니다.
their model serving technique with ORCA
ORCA를 사용한 모델 제공 기술
and they also have fast tensors
또한 빠른 텐서도 있습니다.
which they compare against at Iliuth-Reynman X graph.
Iliuth-Reynman X 그래프와 비교됩니다.
But, as you can see, the VLLM implementation
그러나 보시다시피 VLLM 구현은
which is what's discussed so far
그게 지금까지 논의된 내용이야
supports a much higher batch size
훨씬 더 높은 배치 크기를 지원합니다.
of like, they're supporting like 30 requests
예를 들어 그들은 30개 정도의 요청을 지원하고 있습니다.
in parallel, right, in a sense.
어떤 의미에서는 평행하게, 맞습니다.
So, yeah.
그렇죠.
Yeah, so, yeah.
응, 그렇구나.
Well, how do they, how do they implement it?
글쎄요, 어떻게 구현하나요?
Is it like on Python level or is it on?
Python 수준과 같나요, 아니면 켜져 있나요?
No, it has to be CUDA level.
아니요, CUDA 수준이어야 합니다.
It has to be like CUDA level.
CUDA 수준이어야 합니다.
Because you're messing with that VM right now, right?
지금 당장 그 VM을 망치고 있으니까요, 그렇죠?
No, no, no, okay.
아냐, 아냐, 아냐, 알았어.
So, there is like a way for YouTube defining
따라서 YouTube에서 다음을 정의하는 방법이 있습니다.
like the block mapping stuff like in CUDA level, right?
CUDA 수준의 블록 매핑과 같은 거죠, 그렇죠?
Yeah.
응.
Oh, okay, I see what you're saying.
아, 알겠습니다. 무슨 말인지 알겠습니다.
So, you had to block people on that slide
그래서 그 슬라이드에 있는 사람들을 차단해야 했죠
because you know, there's high probability
알다시피 확률이 높으니까
of this and what happens in ours.
이것과 우리에게 무슨 일이 일어나는지.
Do you know if they also try to use something similar
그들도 비슷한 것을 사용하려고 하는지 아시나요?
to TFB for the, like the table, block table?
테이블과 같은 블록 테이블을 위해 TFB로?
Like, is there a sort of passion for that
예를 들어, 그것에 대한 일종의 열정이 있습니까?
when you think it will be more or?
더 많을 것이라고 생각하면?
I don't think the answer to this question is fine.
이 질문에 대한 대답은 좋지 않다고 생각합니다.
Yeah, so, I'll be moving on to the next paper from there.
네, 그럼 다음 논문으로 넘어가겠습니다.
So, for that, we are done.
이제 우리는 끝났습니다.
So, I had a really good question.
그래서 정말 좋은 질문이 생겼습니다.
So, this mechanism is built on the attention night mechanism.
따라서 이 메커니즘은 Attention Night 메커니즘을 기반으로 구축되었습니다.
The idea is that we can append on subsequent tokens
아이디어는 후속 토큰에 추가할 수 있다는 것입니다.
and keep the computations from earlier.
이전의 계산을 유지합니다.
As you stack transformer layer,
Transformer 레이어를 쌓으면,
like these attention blocks, right?
이런 주의 방해물처럼요, 그렇죠?
The input to the next layer is the output from previous layer
다음 레이어의 입력은 이전 레이어의 출력입니다.
and we sum through Qs.
그리고 우리는 Qs를 통해 합산합니다.
So, that means that the X from previous layers
즉, 이전 레이어의 X가
is not necessarily the same X
반드시 같은 X는 아닙니다
as you get deeper in the model.
모델에 대해 더 깊이 들어갈수록.
Even as you can already continuously.
이미 지속적으로 할 수 있듯이.
So, what happens to performance if we enforce a prior
따라서 사전 조치를 시행하면 성능은 어떻게 되나요?
that like that block is gonna be the same?
그 블록도 똑같을 거에요?
So, the KV cache per se is not what we are modifying.
따라서 KV 캐시 자체는 우리가 수정하는 것이 아닙니다.
Like, the KV cache already existed long before.
마찬가지로 KV 캐시는 오래 전에 이미 존재했습니다.
We are just changing, like, we are essentially
우리는 본질적으로 변화하고 있습니다.
just breaking down KV cache from like
그냥 KV 캐시를 분해하는 것뿐입니다.
contiguous blocks of memory to like smaller pieces, right?
작은 조각을 좋아하는 연속된 메모리 블록이죠, 그렇죠?
Right.
오른쪽.
Yeah, so all of this are based on the fact
네, 그럼 이 모든 것은 사실에 근거한 것입니다
that it's not binary, you know, it's causal.
그것은 이진법이 아니라 인과관계입니다.
So, you have to, because this generation, right?
그래서, 이 세대 때문에, 그렇죠?
And also, like these base models are not encoders.
또한 이러한 기본 모델은 인코더가 아닙니다.
They are decoders.
그들은 디코더입니다.
Yeah, they're decoders only.
네, 디코더일 뿐입니다.
Yeah, that's why you can do this.
그래, 그래서 당신은 이것을 할 수 있습니다.
So, moving on to the next one.
그럼 다음으로 넘어가겠습니다.
So, we already looked at flash attention
그래서 우리는 이미 flash attention을 살펴보았습니다.
and the only reason I'm bringing it back up is
그리고 내가 이 이야기를 다시 꺼내는 유일한 이유는
because the next paper derives from some of the results
다음 논문은 일부 결과에서 파생되기 때문입니다.
in flash attention and like tries to bring
순간적으로 관심을 갖고 가져오려고 합니다.
what flash attention did for the training aspects
훈련 측면에 어떤 플래시 관심이 있었는지
into the inference aspects.
추론 측면에 대해 설명합니다.
So, the reason why flash attention was able
그래서 플래시 어텐션이 가능했던 이유는
to improve the output was, one, because
출력을 향상시키는 것은 하나였습니다. 왜냐하면
they were able to break down the softmax computation
그들은 소프트맥스 계산을 분해할 수 있었습니다
into user terms and the key inside which they brought
사용자 용어와 사용자가 가져온 키에
was that we are not really computation bound,
우리는 실제로 계산에 얽매이지 않았다는 것입니다.
we are memory bound of like,
우리는 기억에 묶여 있습니다.
and the memory operations are what's slowing us down here
여기서 우리의 속도를 늦추는 것은 메모리 작업 때문입니다
and the graph again from the flash attention paper,
그리고 플래시 주목 보고서의 그래프를 다시 살펴보겠습니다.
they showed that instead of writing from the HVM
그들은 HVM에서 쓰는 대신에 그것을 보여주었습니다
into the SRAM and back again and again,
SRAM에 들어갔다가 계속해서 돌아옵니다.
if you create a few scramble which does
몇 가지 스크램블을 생성하면
all of these operations together,
이 모든 작업을 함께 수행하면
we can significantly speed up on attention computations.
주의 계산 속도를 크게 높일 수 있습니다.
So, and also that the matrix multiplication wasn't
그래서, 그리고 또한 행렬 곱셈은 그렇지 않았습니다.
what was consuming most of the time
무엇이 가장 많은 시간을 소비했는지
if you look at the breakdown of the times involved.
관련된 시대의 분석을 보면.
So, what we are looking at is flash decoding
그래서 우리가 보고 있는 것은 플래시 디코딩입니다.
and so the animation is technically
그래서 애니메이션은 기술적으로
destroying flash attention and how it works,
플래시 주의력과 작동 방식을 파괴하고,
but the concern which the authors are trying to address here
하지만 저자가 여기서 다루고자 하는 우려는
is that if you're just doing plain inference
만약 당신이 단지 단순한 추론을 하고 있다면
and you don't have a high batch size,
배치 크기가 크지 않고
much of your GPU can remain unused
GPU의 대부분은 사용되지 않은 채로 남아 있을 수 있습니다.
and the way flash attention was implemented,
플래시 어텐션이 구현된 방식은
you break down the key and B,
키와 B를 분해하면
but you don't really try to break it across batches.
하지만 실제로는 여러 배치로 나누려고 하지 않습니다.
So, the modification which the authors propose
그래서 저자가 제안한 수정안은
is just split it into smaller chunks and recompute it.
단지 그것을 더 작은 덩어리로 나누고 다시 계산하는 것뿐입니다.
So, in flash attention, you had this scalar value
그래서 순간적으로 주의를 기울이면 이 스칼라 값을 갖게 됩니다.
which we were computing along with the usual computation
우리는 일반적인 계산과 함께 계산하고 있었습니다.
so that, like the alpha and beta in a sense,
어떤 의미에서는 알파와 베타처럼
so that you can combine these back in the final set.
최종 세트에서 이를 다시 결합할 수 있습니다.
So, the same thing happens here as well across splits.
따라서 여기에서도 분할 전체에 걸쳐 동일한 일이 발생합니다.
So, you need to keep track of these values
따라서 이 값을 계속 추적해야 합니다.
for each of the splits so that you can combine it
각 분할에 대해 결합할 수 있도록
at the last page.
마지막 페이지에.
Yeah, so on a high level, that is the only change
그래, 그럼 높은 수준에서는 그게 유일한 변화야
within flash decoding, implement splits
플래시 디코딩 내에서 분할 구현
so that you're processing everything in smaller chunks
모든 것을 더 작은 덩어리로 처리하도록
and you need to keep track of this extra scalar
이 추가 스칼라를 추적해야 합니다.
which is the log sum exponential
이는 로그 합계 지수입니다.
and you can compute it back into the final value
최종 값으로 다시 계산할 수 있습니다.
which you should have obtained.
당신이 얻었어야 했던 것.
And by doing this, the reason for doing this
그리고 이렇게 함으로써 이 일을 하는 이유는
is increasing context lengths.
컨텍스트 길이가 늘어나고 있습니다.
So, you can have a single request coming in
따라서 단일 요청이 들어올 수 있습니다.
which is obviously like the Gemini model
확실히 Gemini 모델과 비슷하네요
which I stated with like 10 million context length.
나는 대략 천만 개의 컨텍스트 길이로 언급했습니다.
So, if you have such huge prompt lengths coming in,
그래서 이렇게 엄청난 길이의 프롬프트가 들어오면
flash attention by itself does not do well
순간적인 관심 자체는 잘 되지 않는다
because of the reason stated that
라고 말한 이유 때문에
you're not efficiently utilizing the GPU as you could.
GPU를 최대한 효율적으로 활용하지 못하고 있습니다.
And you can see that from the graphs.
그리고 그래프를 보면 알 수 있습니다.
So, they try naive PyTorch primitive.
그래서 그들은 순진한 PyTorch 프리미티브를 시도합니다.
So, this paper is coming from PyTorch itself.
따라서 이 문서는 PyTorch 자체에서 나온 것입니다.
So, they try PyTorch's own primitives
그래서 그들은 PyTorch 자체의 프리미티브를 시도합니다.
and that actually works better than flash attention
그리고 그것은 실제로 플래시 주의보다 더 잘 작동합니다
in some of the cases.
어떤 경우에는.
And with flash decoding, they are able to preserve
그리고 플래시 디코딩을 사용하면 데이터를 보존할 수 있습니다.
the performance of the model even on significantly higher
훨씬 더 높은 모델에서도 성능이 향상됩니다.
context lengths by just breaking down this computation.
이 계산을 분석하여 컨텍스트 길이를 계산합니다.
And a significant amount of the speedup is just
그리고 상당한 양의 속도 향상은
because of the way flash attention spread it up
플래시의 관심이 그것을 퍼뜨리는 방식 때문에
with the Fuse kernels and stuff like that.
Fuse 커널 등을 사용합니다.
So, they are utilizing like the 50X speedup
그래서 그들은 50X 속도 향상과 같은 것을 활용하고 있습니다.
which just comes from using flash attention
이는 플래시 어텐션을 사용한 결과입니다.
as opposed to the naive implementation of attention,
주의를 순진하게 구현하는 것과는 반대로,
the computations which were reading back and forth
앞뒤로 읽고 있던 계산
into memory.
기억 속으로.
Yeah, and it's still better for larger context lengths
예, 더 긴 컨텍스트 길이에는 여전히 더 좋습니다.
which is the main point here.
이것이 여기서 주요 포인트입니다.
Yeah.
응.
So, what do you mean when you say it's splitting across
그럼 쪼개진다는 말은 무슨 뜻인가요?
KMP?
KMP?
So,
그래서,
In flash attention, you can see like this is happening
순간적으로 주의를 기울이면 이런 일이 일어나는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
as a sequential operation, right?
순차 작업으로요?
For that entire KMB block and in which is fine for training
전체 KMB 블록에 대해 훈련하기에 적합합니다.
but when you're doing inference and you don't have
하지만 추론을 하고 있는데 그럴 만한 정보가 없다면
like you don't have enough batch size
배치 크기가 충분하지 않은 것처럼
to populate your entire GPU.
전체 GPU를 채우려면.
So, what your GPU would essentially end up doing
따라서 GPU가 본질적으로 수행하게 될 작업은 무엇입니까?
is doing this sequentially even though you are essentially
기본적으로는 이 작업을 순차적으로 수행하고 있습니다.
breaking down it into smaller operations, right?
더 작은 작업으로 나누는 거죠, 그렇죠?
So,
그래서,
I don't know if that.
그럴지는 모르겠습니다.
it breaks that down into like multiple for loops going through.
그것은 그것을 통과하는 여러 개의 for 루프로 나눕니다.
So, even if you have a single query coming in,
따라서 단일 쿼리가 들어오더라도
you can handle it better.
당신은 그것을 더 잘 처리할 수 있습니다.
Like you don't have like 10 queries,
검색어가 10개도 없는 것처럼,
like while training you can easily create like 128 batch size
훈련하는 동안 128 배치 크기처럼 쉽게 만들 수 있습니다.
but if you are like there is an aspect of latency
하지만 당신이 원한다면 대기 시간의 측면이 있습니다
involved here, right?
여기에 관련되어 있는 거죠, 그렇죠?
You don't wanna be waiting on batching up like 20 queries
쿼리가 20개 정도 일괄 처리될 때까지 기다리고 싶지는 않을 것입니다.
that are coming in to respond to the first guy.
첫 번째 사람에게 응답하기 위해 오는 것입니다.
Yeah, I guess then in this case you would have to do something
네, 그렇다면 이 경우에는 뭔가 조치를 취해야 할 것 같아요
you have to change that out a little bit actually, right?
실제로는 그것을 조금 바꿔야 합니다. 그렇죠?
Because before you need to do computation,
왜냐하면 계산을 하기 전에,
you already have your first thing, your new first.
당신은 이미 당신의 첫 번째 것, 새로운 첫 번째 것을 가지고 있습니다.
You put your computation on the first count,
당신은 계산을 첫 번째로 세웠고,
but it's in the output data.
하지만 출력 데이터에는 있습니다.
Yeah.
응.
But now you're trying to do everything
그런데 지금 당신은 모든 것을 다 하려고 하고 있어요.
and aggregating them together.
그리고 그것들을 하나로 합칩니다.
Yeah.
응.
So, there's some reduction stuff here or?
그럼 여기에 몇 가지 축소 항목이 있나요?
Yeah, there is a final reduction set.
네, 최종 감소 세트가 있습니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
And that scalar which we are tracking for like the weights
그리고 우리가 추적하고 있는 스칼라는 가중치와 같습니다.
of each of these individual components
이러한 개별 구성 요소 각각의
allows us to do that reduction set.
우리가 감소 세트를 할 수 있게 해줍니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
Yeah.
응.
So, as far as I understand,
그래서 내가 이해하는 한,
so this is basically roughly the same as flash attention
그래서 이것은 기본적으로 플래시 어텐션(Flash Attention)과 거의 같습니다.
just like in some way or place.
어떤 방식이나 장소와 마찬가지로요.
Yeah, this is not a full paper, it's just a blog post.
예, 이것은 전체 논문이 아니며 단지 블로그 게시물일 뿐입니다.
Yeah.
응.
I'm kind of, so this is for processing,
저는 일종의 처리를 위한 것입니다.
like will it long?
오래 갈까요?
Yeah, so the intention is to perform better
응, 그래서 더 나은 성과를 내겠다는 의도야
on like long context lengths and?
긴 컨텍스트 길이와 같은가요?
Long context lengths.
긴 컨텍스트 길이.
Small bad sizes.
작고 나쁜 크기.
For inference.
추론을 위해.
Oh, okay.
아, 그래요.
But does it do better if you're gonna generate
하지만 생성한다면 더 나은 결과를 얻을 수 있을까요?
that long?
그렇게 오래?
Is that what it is?
그게 바로 그거야?
Yeah.
응.
Just specialize for the process and the long input?
프로세스와 긴 입력에만 특화되어 있습니까?
Oh, no, it should work for both.
아, 아뇨, 둘 다에 효과가 있을 겁니다.
It should work for both for the output.
출력 모두에 대해 작동해야합니다.
Yeah.
응.
But like for the output,
하지만 출력과 마찬가지로
you have to generate this long by having this period.
이 기간을 가지고 이만큼 길게 생성해야 합니다.
For the discussion, they only keep it to prompt lengths.
토론을 위해 그들은 프롬프트 길이까지만 보관합니다.
Oh, they only make a term of it's a long prompt.
아, 그들은 긴 프롬프트라는 용어만 사용합니다.
Yeah.
응.
Not with the responses.
응답이 아닙니다.
Oh, okay.
아, 그래요.
Yeah, I just assume the same thing could be done
응, 그냥 똑같은 일이 일어날 수 있을 것 같아
for response, but yeah,
대답을 하자면, 하지만 그래,
since you're building it up incrementally.
점진적으로 구축하고 있기 때문입니다.
Oh, right, right, right.
아, 맞아, 맞아, 맞아.
So same thing.
그래서 같은 것입니다.
Yeah.
응.
What is the question?
질문은 무엇입니까?
So yeah, just wondering, like if this is only applied
그렇군요. 혹시 이것만 적용되는 것인지 궁금합니다.
to like long prompt or long response?
긴 메시지를 좋아하나요, 아니면 긴 응답을 좋아하나요?
Right.
오른쪽.
Oh, I see.
알겠어요.
But it seems like it's the same thing.
하지만 똑같은 것 같습니다.
So the last paper which I'll be diving into
그럼 제가 살펴볼 마지막 논문은
is a continuation of what Rishabh was looking at
리샤브가 보고 있던 것의 연속이다
with respect to speculative decoding.
추측적 디코딩과 관련하여.
So essentially what you're trying to do
본질적으로 당신이 하려는 일은
with speculative decoding was
추측에 의한 디코딩은
instead of having a decoding step
디코딩 단계를 거치는 대신
which only gives you out one token,
하나의 토큰만 제공합니다.
you want to have scenarios where some of the decoding steps
일부 디코딩 단계가 포함된 시나리오를 원합니다.
give you a few more tokens than just a single token.
단일 토큰보다 몇 가지 더 많은 토큰을 제공합니다.
So in effect, you can speed up your inference.
따라서 실제로 추론 속도를 높일 수 있습니다.
So if you just like look back at just like build it up
그러니 만약 네가 쌓아올리듯이 되돌아보고 싶다면
to this point, the Lama tokenizer has 32,000 tokens.
현재까지 Lama 토크나이저에는 32,000개의 토큰이 있습니다.
If you randomly guess what your next token should be,
다음 토큰이 무엇인지 무작위로 추측한다면,
that's like a one in 32,000 chance that you get it right.
그것은 당신이 그것을 맞힐 확률이 32,000분의 1과 같습니다.
But you can do something like in language,
하지만 언어에서는 다음과 같은 일을 할 수 있습니다.
you don't have, all tokens are not equally likely
당신은 가지고 있지 않습니다. 모든 토큰의 확률이 동일하지는 않습니다.
and you can use that distribution to pick something.
그 분포를 사용하여 무언가를 선택할 수 있습니다.
Or another thing is which there are other papers
아니면 또 다른 논문이 있다는 것입니다.
that look at it is use the prompt
그것을 보면 프롬프트를 사용하는 것입니다
to speed up your inference.
추론 속도를 높이려면.
So essentially the idea is that there will be tokens
따라서 본질적으로 아이디어는 토큰이 있다는 것입니다.
from the prompt which repeat within your response.
응답 내에서 반복되는 프롬프트에서.
So you can just speed it up based on that.
따라서 이를 기반으로 속도를 높일 수 있습니다.
That is something which authors have looked at us
그것은 작가들이 우리를 본 것입니다.
and using ngrams as a lookup table
ngram을 조회 테이블로 사용
which we will come to again even in this approach.
이 접근 방식에서도 다시 설명하겠습니다.
And the speculative decoding much of the aspects have gone
그리고 많은 측면의 추측적 디코딩이 사라졌습니다.
into using a smaller draft model or a helper model.
더 작은 초안 모델이나 도우미 모델을 사용합니다.
But it hasn't been widely adopted
하지만 널리 채택되지는 않았습니다.
because of the issues which were again brought up.
다시 제기된 문제 때문이다.
And the complexity of having to manage two different models
그리고 서로 다른 두 모델을 관리해야 하는 복잡성
as well as training it.
훈련할 뿐만 아니라.
So there was a paper which came out
그래서 나온 종이가 있었어요
after speculative decoding called online speculative decoding
추측 디코딩 후 온라인 추측 디코딩이라고 함
which essentially just tries to improve your helper model
본질적으로 도우미 모델을 개선하려고 시도합니다.
to perform better over time.
시간이 지남에 따라 더 나은 성능을 발휘합니다.
And there's also Medusa which tried to look at using
그리고 메두사(Medusa)도 있습니다.
multiple attention heads for doing the process
프로세스 수행을 위한 다중 어텐션 헤드
in a manner that's like easily adoptable.
쉽게 채택할 수 있는 방식으로 말이죠.
And Medusa is a more applied approach
Medusa는 좀 더 적용 가능한 접근 방식입니다.
than speculative decoding with draft models.
초안 모델을 사용한 추측 디코딩보다.
So with that background, we can look at look ahead decoding.
따라서 이러한 배경을 바탕으로 미리보기 디코딩을 살펴볼 수 있습니다.
This is just a graphic which they gave on their website
이것은 그들이 웹사이트에서 제공한 그래픽일 뿐입니다.
of how fast and inference we are looking at
우리가 얼마나 빠르고 추론을 보고 있는지
as compared to the normal decoding process.
일반적인 디코딩 프로세스와 비교됩니다.
And how do we take better guesses is the question
그리고 우리가 어떻게 더 나은 추측을 할 수 있는가가 문제입니다
which we are trying to answer, right?
우리가 대답하려고 하는 것 맞죠?
So yeah, so we're trying to essentially improve
네, 그래서 우리는 본질적으로 개선하려고 노력하고 있습니다.
the token acceptance rate.
토큰 수락률.
So if you have your draft models putting out
따라서 초안 모델을 내놓는 경우
five different tokens and then all of them
5개의 서로 다른 토큰, 그리고 그 토큰 모두
just essentially get discarded
그냥 본질적으로 폐기됩니다
because the main token says this is not what I want.
왜냐하면 메인 토큰이 이것이 내가 원하는 것이 아니라고 말하기 때문입니다.
So it's wasted compute.
그래서 그것은 낭비되는 계산입니다.
So we want to be improving the acceptance rate.
그래서 우리는 수용률을 향상시키고 싶습니다.
And with that, one of the techniques is Jacobi iteration.
그리고 그 기술 중 하나가 야코비 반복(Jacobi iteration)입니다.
So the Jacobi method is something
자코비 방법은 뭔가요
which we would have gone over in high school
우리가 고등학교 때 겪었을 일
if you remember that from a linear algebra.
선형대수학에서 배운 것을 기억한다면요.
But so essentially what the authors propose
그러나 본질적으로 저자가 제안한 것은
is that the core problem which you're trying to solve
그것이 당신이 해결하려는 핵심 문제라는 것입니다
is predicting the M tokens in the response sequence.
응답 시퀀스에서 M개의 토큰을 예측합니다.
So you have an X, you have a Y, which is your response
X가 있고 Y가 있는데 이것이 바로 여러분의 반응입니다.
and you have M tokens there
그리고 거기에 M 토큰이 있습니다
and you're trying to decode that regressively.
그리고 당신은 그것을 회귀적으로 해독하려고 합니다.
And can we do that faster?
그리고 우리는 그것을 더 빨리 할 수 ​​있나요?
Can we just compute all of the tokens in one go
한 번에 모든 토큰을 계산할 수 있나요?
or like a specific set of them in one go?
아니면 한 번에 특정 세트를 좋아하시나요?
For that, they rewrite the regressive decoding model.
이를 위해 그들은 회귀적 디코딩 모델을 다시 작성했습니다.
So essentially for the regressive step,
따라서 본질적으로 회귀 단계에서는
you're trying to look at what is the token
당신은 토큰이 무엇인지 보려고합니다
which I should output given that
내가 출력해야 할 것은
I have this particular input, right?
나한테 이런 특정한 입력이 있는 거죠, 그렇죠?
And as we go for like further steps
그리고 우리가 다음 단계로 나아가면서
as you're building out your response,
답변을 작성하는 동안
you do that for each particular token.
각 특정 토큰에 대해 그렇게 합니다.
So they define a function
그래서 그들은 함수를 정의합니다.
which is shown here
여기에 표시된 것은
and they convert it into that form.
그리고 그들은 그것을 그 형태로 변환합니다.
So you essentially have a system of nonlinear equations
따라서 본질적으로 비선형 방정식 시스템이 있습니다.
which you're trying to solve.
당신이 해결하려고하는 것입니다.
The Jacobi method, if you do remember linear algebra
선형대수학을 기억한다면 야코비 방법(Jacobi method)
is applied to a system of linear equations.
선형 방정식 시스템에 적용됩니다.
And that is actually an issue in the description
그리고 그것은 실제로 설명의 문제입니다.
of this paper because they link to the normal Jacobi method
이 논문의 내용은 일반적인 Jacobi 방법과 연결되어 있기 때문입니다.
like the link to the Wikipedia page
Wikipedia 페이지 링크처럼
with the normal Jacobi method, which is this.
이것은 일반적인 Jacobi 방법을 사용하는 것입니다.
Like this is what you study in high school
고등학교 때 공부하는 게 이런 거야
of how to use the Jacobi method,
Jacobi 방법을 사용하는 방법,
but it applies to only linear equations.
그러나 이는 선형 방정식에만 적용됩니다.
And what you essentially end up doing for a refresher
그리고 본질적으로 재충전을 위해 무엇을 하게 되는지
is that once you rewrite the system of equations
방정식 시스템을 다시 작성하면
into each variable, once you represent it in this form,
각 변수에 이 형식으로 표현하면
you take an initial guess of what each token is
각 토큰이 무엇인지 초기 추측합니다.
and then you iteratively, like similar to Newton-Raphson
그런 다음 Newton-Raphson과 비슷하게 반복적으로
or any of those iterative methods,
또는 그러한 반복적인 방법 중 하나,
you try to iteratively solve the system of equations
방정식 시스템을 반복적으로 풀려고 합니다.
and once your method converges,
방법이 수렴되면
you have all the tokens which you need.
필요한 모든 토큰이 있습니다.
And but this is for linear systems
그러나 이것은 선형 시스템에 대한 것입니다.
and the only reference which I could find to do this
그리고 이 작업을 수행하기 위해 내가 찾을 수 있는 유일한 참조는
for nonlinear equations was this particular book.
비선형 방정식에 대해서는 이 특별한 책이 있었습니다.
And yeah, they essentially say that
그리고 네, 그들은 본질적으로 이렇게 말합니다
you can do the linear method for the nonlinear system
비선형 시스템에 대해 선형 방법을 사용할 수 있습니다.
and it does work the same way.
그리고 그것은 같은 방식으로 작동합니다.
And one property of this computation
그리고 이 계산의 한 가지 속성은
is that with every step, you solve one of the variables
모든 단계에서 변수 중 하나를 해결한다는 것입니다.
and with m steps, you can solve the entire equation,
m 단계를 거치면 전체 방정식을 풀 수 있습니다.
but that is essentially same as regressively doing it
하지만 이는 본질적으로 회귀적으로 수행하는 것과 동일합니다.
because if you had to take m steps,
왜냐하면 만약 당신이 m걸음을 걸어야 한다면,
it is same as just a sequentially,
순차적으로 하는 것과 동일합니다.
but in this case, you're solving a system of equations
하지만 이 경우에는 방정식 시스템을 풀고 있습니다.
to get to that.
그것에 도달하기 위해.
That's the difference in Jacobi iteration
이것이 Jacobi 반복의 차이점입니다.
and this is algorithm from that book
그리고 이건 그 책에 나온 알고리즘이에요
about how do you do parallelize
병렬화하는 방법에 대해
the nonlinear Jacobi iteration.
비선형 야코비 반복.
Yeah, so just to do that visually,
예, 시각적으로 확인하려면
this is what would happen if we do Jacobi iteration.
Jacobi 반복을 수행하면 이런 일이 발생합니다.
You have your prompt and then you take a guess
프롬프트를 받은 다음 추측을 합니다.
of what the other tokens are.
다른 토큰은 무엇입니까?
This is like your initial guess in the Jacobi method
이것은 Jacobi 방법의 초기 추측과 같습니다.
and you just are randomly filling that out
그리고 당신은 무작위로 그것을 채우고 있습니다
of what you think the next token should be.
다음 토큰이 무엇이어야 한다고 생각하시나요?
And then the issue again here is that
그리고 여기서 다시 문제는
you're saying that the operations are,
당신은 수술이
like the memory operations are what are taking time,
메모리 작업에 시간이 걸리는 것처럼
so you want to optimize the GPU as much as possible.
그래서 GPU를 최대한 최적화하고 싶습니다.
So computations is not a concern in this particular case
따라서 이 특별한 경우에는 계산이 문제가 되지 않습니다.
and we are particularly looking at models
우리는 특히 모델을 보고 있습니다.
where you want to improve the latency
대기 시간을 개선하고 싶은 경우
and there is an increased amount of computations
그리고 계산량이 늘어나서
which will happen as we go into the actual model,
실제 모델에 들어가면 이런 일이 발생합니다.
but that is not something you should look at here
하지만 그건 여기서 봐야 할 내용이 아닙니다
because the concern is latency in this particular case.
왜냐하면 이 특별한 경우에는 대기 시간이 문제이기 때문입니다.
So now you don't have a draft model again in this case,
이제 이 경우 초안 모델이 다시는 없습니다.
it's just your main model predicting these.
이를 예측하는 것은 단지 주요 모델일 뿐입니다.
So your main model says that the next token
그래서 당신의 메인 모델은 다음 토큰이
to Alan Turing is like the next token should be is
Alan Turing에게 다음 토큰은 다음과 같습니다.
and then you have parallelized the operation
그런 다음 작업을 병렬화했습니다.
by having a few random tokens which you guessed
당신이 추측한 몇 개의 무작위 토큰을 가짐으로써
and then you're asking the model
그리고 모델에게 물어보시죠
to parallelly compute these as well.
이것들도 병렬로 계산합니다.
So the model says if this was who,
모델은 이렇게 말합니다. 만약 이 사람이 누구라면,
then the next token should be yes.
그러면 다음 토큰은 yes여야 합니다.
If it's yes, it should be A and so on
그렇다면 A여야 합니다.
for as many tokens you guessed.
당신이 추측한 만큼의 토큰에 대해.
So this is the parameter which we'll set later
이것이 나중에 설정할 매개변수입니다.
of like how many do we want to guess forward,
앞으로 얼마나 많은 숫자를 추측하고 싶은지,
but the model computes what the next should be
하지만 모델은 다음 단계가 무엇인지 계산합니다.
and if we let it continue,
계속 놔두면
we use the new generated tokens as the,
우리는 새로 생성된 토큰을 다음과 같이 사용합니다.
like we updated with the random selection
무작위 선택으로 업데이트한 것처럼
and now we have one step forward.
이제 우리는 한 단계 앞으로 나아갔습니다.
Like in the previous step,
이전 단계와 마찬가지로,
we only got one accepted token
우리는 승인된 토큰을 하나만 얻었습니다
and the rest of it was wasted computation.
나머지는 낭비된 계산이었습니다.
So there was no merit to doing that,
그러니 그렇게 할 가치가 없었어요.
but except we updated our randomly selected initial guess
하지만 무작위로 선택한 초기 추측을 업데이트했다는 점만 제외하면
and similar to the computation,
계산과 유사합니다.
we solved one variable,
우리는 하나의 변수를 해결했습니다.
but the remaining variables are still kind of random
하지만 나머지 변수는 여전히 무작위입니다.
and we still haven't controls yet.
아직 제어할 수 없습니다.
And now the model has to look at all of these variables
이제 모델은 이러한 모든 변수를 살펴봐야 합니다.
and try to compute what the next open would be
다음 번 오픈이 무엇인지 계산해 보세요.
if this was the particular variable in this spot.
이것이 이 지점의 특정 변수라면.
So again, we do the same step, we continue
다시 한 번 동일한 단계를 수행하고 계속합니다.
and then in cases where
그리고 그런 경우에는
yeah, I believe this step fails as well.
네, 이 단계도 실패할 것 같아요.
So in this particular case,
따라서 이 특별한 경우에는
you're essentially just rewriting and every step
본질적으로 다시 작성하고 모든 단계를 수행하는 것입니다.
you're only getting one new token accepted,
단 하나의 새 토큰만 허용됩니다.
but when you have a scenario where the next token,
하지만 다음 토큰이
which the main model predicts is same as that
메인 모델이 예측하는 것과 동일합니다.
which you're getting via speculative decoding,
추측성 디코딩을 통해 얻은 결과입니다.
you can have multiple tokens be accepted,
여러 개의 토큰을 허용할 수 있습니다.
which was again the objective which we set out with
이는 다시 우리가 세운 목표였습니다.
of like having a few steps
몇 걸음만 걷는 것 같은
where more than one token gets accepted.
두 개 이상의 토큰이 허용되는 경우.
And the rest of it is just wasted computation.
나머지는 낭비되는 계산일 뿐입니다.
So we have re-rated there,
그래서 우리는 그곳에서 다시 평가를 받았습니다.
but on the last step, we accepted two tokens.
하지만 마지막 단계에서 우리는 두 개의 토큰을 수락했습니다.
So this is naively doing Jacobi iteration.
그래서 이것은 순진하게 Jacobi 반복을 수행하는 것입니다.
What the authors propose is a bit more complicated.
저자가 제안하는 것은 좀 더 복잡합니다.
So instead of all of that wasted computation,
따라서 낭비되는 모든 계산 대신
what if you saved the trajectory
궤적을 저장했다면 어떨까요?
which the model was trying to take?
그 모델은 어떤 것을 찍으려고 했죠?
As in you save the n-grams.
마찬가지로 n-gram을 저장합니다.
If you're computing using the main model
기본 모델을 사용하여 계산하는 경우
what the next token should be,
다음 토큰은 무엇이어야 하는지,
you just see it like in this case,
이 경우에는 이렇게 보입니다.
it's a two-gram, so it's very similar to recuperation
2그램이라 회복과 매우 비슷해요
and we will be dealing with higher ends,
우리는 더 높은 목적을 다룰 것입니다.
but just for visualization,
하지만 시각화를 위해서만
you have a two-gram being created
2그램이 생성되고 있습니다
and what you can do is before discarding everything,
그리고 당신이 할 수 있는 일은 모든 것을 버리기 전에,
you can have a look at the two-grams which you have stored
당신은 당신이 저장한 2그램을 볼 수 있습니다
and then use that as your vet of what the next token is
그런 다음 그것을 다음 토큰이 무엇인지 조사하는 데 사용하십시오.
and use that to continue forward.
이를 사용하여 계속 진행하세요.
In the iteration.
반복에서.
What happens when there are conflicting ones?
상충되는 내용이 있으면 어떻게 되나요?
Is that on the next slide?
다음 슬라이드에 있나요?
But at least for the visualization,
하지만 적어도 시각화를 위해서는
you have a case where you only have one case
당신은 케이스가 하나뿐인 케이스가 있습니다
which matches that one.
그 것과 일치하는 것.
Oh, so basically this is like a cache, right?
아, 기본적으로 이것은 캐시와 같습니다. 그렇죠?
Yeah, you have a cache implemented.
예, 캐시가 구현되었습니다.
You roughly know what the target model is based on.
대상 모델의 기반이 무엇인지 대략적으로 알 수 있습니다.
Yeah, because we don't have a draft model
응, 초안 모델이 없으니까
and it's all the target model's distribution happening, right?
타겟 모델의 분포가 모두 일어나는 거죠, 그렇죠?
But there are some failure cases
하지만 실패하는 경우도 있어요
where this two-gram can happen in two places.
이 2그램은 두 곳에서 발생할 수 있습니다.
Yeah, so when it happens in two places,
네, 두 곳에서 그런 일이 발생하면
you need to do a verification step
확인 단계를 거쳐야 합니다
and the actual implementation is way more complex than this
실제 구현은 이보다 훨씬 더 복잡합니다.
because this is a two-gram
이건 2그램이니까
which makes it very similar to speculative decoding,
이는 추측적 디코딩과 매우 유사합니다.
but the actual case is an n-gram.
하지만 실제 사례는 n-gram입니다.
So in this particular case,
따라서 이 특별한 경우에는
you have the n being set to four,
n이 4로 설정되어 있고,
so you end up with a four-gram
그래서 결국 4그램이 되는 거죠
with like, yeah.
예.
So the numbers are meaningless,
그러니 숫자는 의미가 없고,
please don't look at that.
제발 그걸 보지 마세요.
The numbers essentially just say
숫자는 본질적으로 말해줍니다
what is the position of this particular token
이 특정 토큰의 위치는 무엇입니까
with respect to the initial token
초기 토큰과 관련하여
in the prediction process.
예측 과정에서.
And so a valid n-gram in this particular case would be,
따라서 이 특별한 경우에 유효한 n-그램은 다음과 같습니다.
let's say you have one, two, three,
하나, 둘, 셋이 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
and then whatever's happening at this step.
그리고 이 단계에서 무슨 일이 일어나든 말이죠.
So we are on the last step of the Jacob iteration
이제 우리는 Jacob 반복의 마지막 단계에 있습니다.
where the verification step will happen.
확인 단계가 발생하는 곳입니다.
So that's why the fourth token
그래서 네 번째 토큰이
is not really there in the diagram,
실제로는 다이어그램에 없지만
but you essentially have an n-gram being created
하지만 본질적으로 n-gram이 생성되고 있습니다.
and you also have to predict the next token
그리고 다음 토큰도 예측해야 합니다
based on what has happened.
일어난 일을 바탕으로.
And there are two parameters in this entire problem.
그리고 이 전체 문제에는 두 가지 매개변수가 있습니다.
There's window size of how far we are looking at.
우리가 얼마나 멀리 보고 있는지에 대한 창 크기가 있습니다.
So that determines how many new tokens
그래서 얼마나 많은 새로운 토큰이 결정되는지를 결정합니다.
you are generating on each step.
당신은 각 단계에서 생성하고 있습니다.
So in this case, you have five,
따라서 이 경우에는 5개가 있습니다.
so that's why the window size is five.
그래서 창 크기가 5인 이유입니다.
And the n-gram size is controlling
그리고 n-gram 크기가 제어하고 있습니다.
how much of the history you're retaining.
당신이 얼마나 많은 역사를 유지하고 있는지.
So you are constructing a four-gram,
그래서 당신은 4그램을 만들고 있습니다.
so that's why the n-gram size is four there.
이것이 바로 n-gram 크기가 4인 이유입니다.
And now if you have scenarios
이제 시나리오가 있다면
where there are multiple correct n-grams to choose from,
선택할 수 있는 올바른 n-그램이 여러 개 있는 경우
then you need to do verification.
그런 다음 확인을 해야 합니다.
So in this particular case,
따라서 이 특별한 경우에는
there is an additional parameter called g,
g라는 추가 매개변수가 있습니다.
which is how many you choose to verify.
확인하기로 선택한 개수입니다.
In all the experiments, the authors choose set it to w,
모든 실험에서 저자는 이를 w로 설정하도록 선택했습니다.
the window size is same as the number of things
창 크기는 사물의 수와 같습니다
you choose to verify.
확인을 선택합니다.
And what this shows is the attention mask.
그리고 이것이 보여주는 것은 주의 마스크입니다.
The only thing it is essentially saying is that,
본질적으로 말하는 유일한 것은 다음과 같습니다.
same as causal attention,
인과적 관심과 동일
you are only looking at the tokens before it.
당신은 그 앞에 있는 토큰만 보고 있을 뿐입니다.
So the token one can only see itself and zero.
따라서 토큰 1은 자신과 0만 볼 수 있습니다.
And the same thing is done for all of the steps.
그리고 모든 단계에서 동일한 작업이 수행됩니다.
So, and the verification branch cannot look at anything
따라서 검증 지점에서는 아무것도 볼 수 없습니다.
in the lookahead branch,
미리보기 지점에서,
which is why it's all masked out.
그래서 모든 것이 가려져 있습니다.
And then you have it, again,
그리고 다시, 당신은 그것을 갖게 됩니다.
only attending to its previous tokens
이전 토큰에만 주의
and just starting to do this.
그리고 이제 막 이 일을 시작하고 있어요.
You are verifying, you only have zero at this step
확인 중입니다. 이 단계에서는 0만 있습니다.
and everything else is happening through
그 밖의 모든 일은 다음을 통해 일어나고 있습니다.
like iteratively.
마치 반복적으로.
So this is for the verification branch
그래서 이것은 검증 지점을 위한 것입니다.
and this is the lookahead stuff which is happening.
이것이 바로 지금 일어나고 있는 예측입니다.
And they just combine it together into one parallel step
그리고 그들은 그것을 하나의 병렬 단계로 결합합니다.
to do it efficiently.
효율적으로 하려고.
And yeah, so this is just a comparison
그리고 네, 이건 단지 비교일 뿐입니다
of what the attention mask looks like
주의 마스크가 어떻게 생겼는지
when you compare it with Medusa.
메두사와 비교해 보면요.
So in Medusa, you have multiple heads
메두사에는 머리가 여러 개 있습니다
and like if the first head says that
그리고 첫 번째 머리가 그렇게 말한다면
the next token can be gate par i
다음 토큰은 게이트 파 i가 될 수 있습니다
of like a case where we are taking only the two ones,
두 가지만 선택하는 경우와 같이
the next head will again continue from it
다음 머리는 다시 계속 될 것입니다
and say three tokens.
토큰 세 개를 말하세요.
And for the i case, it will again generate three tokens
i 경우에는 다시 3개의 토큰이 생성됩니다.
and that's what the attention mask looks like there.
그리고 그것이 바로 주의 마스크의 모습입니다.
To contrast with what this attention mask looks like.
이 주의 마스크가 보이는 것과 대조됩니다.
Yeah, I'm mostly but I've been up.
응, 난 대부분 깨어있지만 깨어 있었어.
So the scaling law is something which they discuss
그래서 스케일링 법칙은 그들이 논의하는 것입니다.
based on the results of this paper.
이 논문의 결과를 바탕으로.
So what they find is that if you have sufficiently large N
그래서 그들이 찾은 것은 N이 충분히 크다면
and you exponentially increase the builder size,
빌더 크기를 기하급수적으로 늘리면
you can get a linear trend in the step compression.
단계 압축에서 선형 추세를 얻을 수 있습니다.
So you can linearly reduce the number of decoding steps
따라서 디코딩 단계 수를 선형적으로 줄일 수 있습니다.
which is required.
이는 필수입니다.
So that's a result which they find
그래서 그들이 찾아낸 결과가 바로 이것이다.
with their experimentation.
그들의 실험으로.
And what impact does this have?
그리고 이것이 어떤 영향을 미치나요?
So they applied it on Lama Chat model
그래서 라마챗 모델에 적용했어요
and they observed a speedup of 1.5x
1.5배의 속도 향상을 관찰했습니다.
and latency reductions on human eval
인간 평가에 대한 대기 시간 감소
as well as the math problems.
수학 문제도 그렇고.
Yeah, that's GSM 8K.
네, GSM 8K입니다.
So yeah, so it does reduce latency
그렇군요. 그러면 대기 시간이 줄어듭니다.
which was the primary target of this entire thing.
이것이 이 모든 일의 주요 목표였습니다.
So wasted computations again, it's not a concern here.
다시 계산을 낭비하므로 여기서는 문제가 되지 않습니다.
You're just trying to efficiently utilize most of the GPS.
당신은 대부분의 GPS를 효율적으로 활용하려고 노력하고 있습니다.
So for my part, we see that LLM inference
그래서 저는 LLM 추론을 봅니다.
was bottlenecked by memory constraints
메모리 제약으로 인해 병목 현상이 발생했습니다.
and we saw how we can go about building
그리고 우리는 건물을 짓는 방법을 보았습니다.
a more efficient KV cache.
보다 효율적인 KV 캐시.
The authors also had to implement like the kernel
저자는 또한 커널처럼 구현해야 했습니다.
for blockwise attention or like page detention
블록 단위 주의 또는 페이지 유지와 같은 경우
as they call it.
그들이 부르는대로.
The next paper looked at flash decoding
다음 논문에서는 플래시 디코딩을 살펴보았습니다.
which was trying to bring the enhancements
향상된 기능을 가져오려고 했던 것입니다.
of flash attention V1 and V2 into the inference step.
플래시 어텐션 V1과 V2를 추론 단계로 전환합니다.
And the last paper which we looked at
그리고 우리가 마지막으로 본 논문은
was look ahead decoding
미리보기 디코딩 중이었어
which is trying to improve speculative decoding
추측성 디코딩을 개선하려고 노력하고 있는 것입니다.
but take a different approach
하지만 다른 접근 방식을 취하세요
rather than using draft models
초안 모델을 사용하는 것보다
and yeah, for latency critical applications
네, 대기 시간이 중요한 애플리케이션의 경우
because there's a lot of wasted computations happening.
낭비되는 계산이 많이 발생하기 때문입니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.